Finding Aid for William Herbert Hobbs Papers, 1884-1950
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
William Herbert Hobbs Papers 1884-1950 1919-1941
Hobbs, William Herbert, 1864-1952.
851610 Aa 2
Professor of Geology at the University of Michigan, also chairman of the Ann Arbor Branch of the National Security League during World War I. His papers contain correspondence and other materials concerning his activities with the National Security League, his interest in Arctic geology and exploration, and his dispute over the political views of Charles Lindbergh. The collection also includes numerous manuscripts of published and unpublished books and articles, notebooks, 1921-1922, detailing the University of Michigan expedition to the Pacific and travel notes of trips to the Near East, Spain, the West Indies, and Switzerland.
2 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The papers were donated in several accessions by Professor Hobbs (donor no. 586 ); by the U-M Dept. of Geology (donor no. 1871 ); and by Herbert C. Crandell (donor no. 9508 ).
The collection is open to research.
William Herbert Hobbs served as a professor of geology and director of the geology laboratory at the University of Michigan from 1906 to 1934. Born in Worchester, Massachusetts on July 2, 1864, he received a Bachelor of Science degree from Worchester Polytechnical Institute in 1883. He completed both master's and doctoral degrees at Johns Hopkins University. Before coming to Michigan, he served as curator of the geology museum and professor of mineralogy, metallurgy, and petrology at the University of Wisconsin.
Widely known for scientific expeditions to Greenland and worldwide geological research, he was also politically active, serving as chairman of the Ann Arbor branch of the National Security League during World War I. Many land formations have been named after Hobbs by explorer friends, including a mountain, several glaciers, and a strip of coastline in Antarctica.
In 1921, he charted little-known islands held by Japan with the help of the Japanese navy, information which became valuable to the U.S. government during World War II. For his scholarly and personal contributions, France awarded him the Chevalier Legion Honor in 1924. While at the University of Michigan, Hobbs led expeditions to Greenland in 1926, 1927, and 1928 to research his theories on the influence of the Greenland ice cap on weather. During the 1928 expedition, Hobbs participated in the rescue of two men whose plane had been forced down in Greenland during a trans-Atlantic flight.
In 1950, Hobbs donated his collection of approximately 750 publications on polar expeditions to the University Library. Hobbs himself had written 15 books and many articles on geological and political issues. He died in Ann Arbor, MI on January 1, 1953, at the age of 88.
The William Herbert Hobbs papers contain correspondence and other materials concerning his activities with the National Security League, his interest in Arctic geology and exploration, and his dispute over the political views of Charles Lindbergh. The collection also includes numerous manuscripts of published and unpublished books and articles, notebooks, 1921-1922, detailing the University of Michigan expedition to the Pacific and travel notes of trips to the Near East, Spain, the West Indies, and Switzerland.
This collection is divided up into six series: Correspondence, Personal Materials, Political Materials, Professional Activities, Writings, and Photographs.
Subjects:
Arctic regions.; Geology--Arctic regions.; Hobbs, William Herbert, 1864-1952.; Lindbergh, Charles A. (Charles Augustus), 1902-1974.; National Security League.; National Security League. Ann Arbor Branch (Mich.); Voyages and travels.; Travelers.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Geology.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Wise, Stephen S. (Stephen Samuel), 1874-1949.; World War, 1914-1918.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Caroline Islands.; Cook Islands.; Expeditions and surveys.; Hobbs, William Herbert, 1864-1952.; Yap (Micronesia); University of Michigan--Expeditions and surveys.
Contributors:
Alden, William C. (William Clinton), b. 1871.; Alger, Frederick Moulton, 1876-1933.; Freuchen, Peter, 1886-1957.; Menken, S. Stanwood, 1870-; Mitchell, Hugh Chester, 1877-1956.; Peary, Robert E. (Robert Edwin), 1856-1920.; Putnam, George Haven, 1844-1930.; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919.; Smith, William Alden, 1859-1932.; Stefansson, Vilhjalmur, 1879-1962.; Stimson, Henry L. (Henry Lewis), 1867-1950.; Townsend, Charles E. (Charles Elroy), 1856-1924.; Winter, John Garrett, 1881-1956.; Wood, Henry A. Wise (Henry Alexander Wise), 1866-1939.; Wood, Leonard, 1860-1927.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Correspondence
  The series of Correspondence (0.5 linear ft.) is organized chronologically, with folders of correspondence on specific subjects interfiled. Some correspondence can also be found in folders labeled "Papers" on a particular subject. An index of selected correspondents follows the contents list.
  - 1884 undated (Box 1)
    (microfilm copy available)
  - May-June 1913, concerning engineering course in Geology (Box 1)
  - 1915, regarding the founding of the American Association of University Professors (Box 1)
  - October-December 1915 (Box 1)
  - January-February 1916 (Box 1)
  - March-June 1916 (Box 1)
  - July-December 1916 (Box 1)
  - January-March 1917 (Box 1)
  - April-December 1917 (Box 1)
  - 1918-1919 (Box 1)
  - December 1918-March 1919, with Alfred H. Lloyd concerning Hobbs' war lectures (Box 1)
  - 1936-1938, with the MacMillan Co. regarding law suit of Dr. F.A. Cook over publication of Hobbs' Peary (Box 1)
  - 1936-1948, concerning controversy with Gerald Seligman (Box 1)
  - January-June 1937 (Box 1)
  - July-December 1937 (Box 1)
  - 1939 concerning Antarctica articles (Box 1)
  - 1941, concerning airplane flights to Europe via Greenland (Box 1)
  - January-March 1943 (Box 1)
  - April-June 1943 (Box 1)
  - July-August 1943 (Box 1)
  - September-October 1943 (Box 1)
  - November-December 1943 (Box 1)
  - 1944-1945 (Box 1)
  - January-June 1946 (Box 1)
  - July-December 1946 (Box 1)
  - January-March 1947 (Box 1)
  - 1948-1950 (Box 1)
  - 1950, concerning dispute over article critical of Hobbs in "Transactions American Geophysical Union" (Box 1)
- Personal Materials
  Personal Materials (0.2 linear ft.) contain materials related to William Hobbs' interests and life. This series contains his autobiography, poetry he wrote, as well as passports and travel documents.
  - A Biographic Chronology of William Herbert Hobbs 1943 (Box 1)
  - Library of Polar Books to be donated to the University of Michigan 1936 (Box 1)
  - Miscellanea (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings concerning rescue of trans-Atlantic flyers in Greenland 1928 (Box 1)
  - Personal poetry (Box 1)
  - Travel documents, including passports, fragments of travel journals (Box 1)
- Political Materials
  The Political Materials series (0.2 linear ft.) consists mostly of documents pertaining to the Ann Arbor branch of the National Security League, for which Hobbs served as chairman, as well as political issues and controversies that involved or interested Hobbs. This series includes a folder of material on his dispute with Charles Lindbergh over political views.
  - National Security League
    - Constitution and Printed Material of the National Security League (Box 1)
    - Membership lists of the National Security League, Ann Arbor Branch (Box 1)
    - Minutes and Financial Records of the National Security League, Ann Arbor branch 1915-1919 (Box 1)
    - Resolutions adopted by the National Security League 1915-1917 (Box 1)
    - Speeches and Speech Introductions to meeting of the National Security League 1916-1917 (Box 1)
  - Volume of clippings and writings concerning World War I 1915-1921 (Box 1)
  - Papers concerning controversy with Rabbi Stephen G. Wise 1921 (Box 1)
  - Writings on the Ford-Lincoln controversy 1923 (Box 1)
  - Papers concerning the defense of Greenland 1940-1941 (Box 2)
  - Papers concerning controversy with Charles A. Lindbergh over political views 1941 (Box 2)
- Professional Activities
  The Professional Activities series (0.6 linear ft.) consists of notebooks containing notes on the University of Michigan expedition to the Pacific and many other trips to the Near East, Spain, the West Indies, and Switzerland.
  - Notebooks
    - Notes on University of Michigan Pacific Expedition 1921-1922, 5 volumes (Box 2)
    - Notes on Pacific Island Expedition 1923 (Box 2)
    - Notes on West Indies trip 1922 (Box 2)
    - Geological notes on trip through Spain circa 1905 (Box 2)
    - Notes on trip through the Mediterranean area and the Near East 1913 (Box 2)
    - Notes on European trip 1925 (Box 2)
    - Notes on trip through Switzerland undated (Box 2)
  - Notes for lecture on lakes undated (Box 2)
  - Notes on petrographic geology (Box 2)
  - Lectures for a course on Historical Geology 1906-1907 (Box 2)
  - Lectures presented in Delft, Holland 1922 (Box 2)
  - International Glacier Commission 1931-1934 (Box 2)
    (Hobbs was Vice-President)
  - Trans-Arctic aviation 1936-1937 (Box 2)
  - Papers concerning book "Matthew Henson, Dark Companion" 1947 (Box 2)
    (includes detailed correspondence with Vilhjalmur Stefansson and Peter Freuchen)
  - Papers concerning articles on Arctic climates 1948 (Box 2)
  - Research Data on Desert Processes 1916 (Box 2)
- Writings
  The Writings series consists mostly of manuscripts of books and articles written by Hobbs
  - Articles on Continental Glaciers (Box 2)
  - Articles on Explorers, Exploration (Box 2)
  - Abstracts of articles on polar expedition (Box 2)
  - "A Scientist's Pilgrimage", Original Manuscript (Box 2)
  - "The Glaciers of Mountain and Continent", unpublished manuscript (Box 2)
  - "The Geological Character Lines of Landscapes", manuscript (Box 2)
  - "Peary-The Engineer", unpublished manuscript (Box 2)
  - "A Cheap, Portable Method of Obtaining Hydrogen", by D.S. McKenzie May 1932 (Box 2)
  - "The University and the Wars", Manuscript 1937 (Box 2)
  - Articles concerning Antarctica 1939-1941 (Box 2)
  - Published articles (Box 2)
  - Book Reviews (Box 2)
  - Criticism of "The War with Germany" by L.P. Ayres 1919 (Box 2)
  - Writings on Charles Wilford Cook, Trans-Atlantic Flying Routes, National Defense, Geology Department at University of Michigan (Box 2)
  - Volume of Scientific Writings, also includes Hobbs Family genealogy 1935-1939 (Box 2)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series (0.4 linear ft.) contains both personal and professional images. Two folders hold photographs from an expedition to the Marshall Islands. Another folder contains captioned photos used in a book written by Hobbs.
  - Marshall Islands?, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Personal photographs (Box 2)
  - Original photographs for his book 1950s, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Mt. Lassen Eruption, California 1915 (Box 2)
  - Photograph of A. Wegener, Hobbs, Parker D. Cramer, A. Berson. Berlin 1928 (Box 2)
    autographed by all
Selective index of correspondents
Alden, William C. (William Clinton), 1871-1959
January 18, 1943
Alger, Frederick Moulton, 1876-1933
March 24, 1917
Menken, S. Stanwood, 1870-1954
November 15, 19, and 23, 1915, January 10, 1916, February 14, 1916, January 3, 1917, February 1, 1917
Mitchell, Hugh Chester, 1877-1956
May, June, and July, 1937
Peary, Robert E. (Robert Edwin), 1856-1920
February 1916, November 22, 1919
Putnam, George Haven, 1844-1930
1915, January 4, 1916, January 8, 1917
Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919
March 5 and 8, 1917
Smith, William Alden, 1859-1932
January 5, 1916, March 2, 1916, April 4, 1917
Stefansson, Vilhjalmur, 1879-1962
1937
Stimson, Henry Lewis, 1867-1950
April 5, 1917
Townsend, Charles Elroy, 1856-1924
1916
Winter, John Garrett, 1881-1956
1918
Wood, Henry A. (Henry Alexander Wise), 1866-1939
1915, 1916
Wood, Leonard, 1860-1927
1916, March 1, 1917, April 2, 1917